Guide to the Browning Photograph Collection 1918-1952 (bulk, 1920-1938) PR 9
New-York Historical Society
Browning photograph collection
1918-1952 (bulk, 1920-1938)
New-York Historical Society
Browning, Irving, 1895-1961
Irving Browning Studio
PR 9
7 Linear feet (27 boxes)
The Browning Collection consists primarily of photographs of interiors and exteriors of 1920s and 1930s New York buildings, including art deco theaters, hotels, skyscrapers, suburban residences, shops, and institutions. Also captured are Manhattan shoppers and window displays, Lower East Side peddlers, advertising sandwich boards, roof tops, Great Depression shanty towns and street life, dramatic skylines, night views, weather, sports, many types of transportation, and photomontages. Documents and ephemera in the collection relate to Irving Browning's professional career as a photographer and cinematographer. The Browning Photograph Collection is digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Irving Browning in the name of Irving and the late Sam Browning, July 29, 1959.
Arrangement
Materials are organized in two series:
Series I. Photographs
Series II. Documents
Biographical Note
Irving Browning (1895-1961), a self-taught photographer and cinematographer, was born in New York City. Browning opened a commercial photograph studio at 110 West 40th Street in 1922 or 1923; his younger brother, Sam, occasionally worked with him as a photographer. A former silent film actor and comedian of the 1910s, New Yorker Irving Browning photographed both exteriors and interiors of skyscrapers, art deco theaters, hotels, apartment buildings, and suburban residences, and documented the lifestyles of New Yorkers during the 1920s and 1930s.
The Irving Browning Studio received commissions from architectural firms, advertising agencies, and magazines to photographically illustrate both the realistic and idealistic urban environment of Depression-era New York City. As construction in Manhattan flourished despite the Depression, Browning was hired to document such new architectural landmarks as the Chrysler Building, the Waldorf-Astoria Hotel, the RKO Roxy and Earl Carroll theaters, and the towering Empire State Building.
Through both his professional and personal work, Browning also captured some of the more intimate daily experiences of city residents. Many of his photographs from the 1930s meditate on the contrasts of poverty and wealth; they focus on poor Lower East Side peddlers, former businessmen selling apples in the aftermath of the stock market crash, and shantytowns as well as on such things as well-heeled shoppers perusing fashionable window displays and the leisure activities and lifestyles of the wealthy.
Browning was an innovator who took an avid interest in the technical aspects of photography. His correspondence hints at his interest in the evolution of color film, in advances in motion picture technologies, and in expanding the ability of still photographs to communicate. Browning's creative and sometimes frenetic photomontages were popular among magazine advertising clients. His novel circular reflection, bas-relief, and expansive architectural views graced the pages of The New York Times. Browning's technical interests also extended to the history of photography and cinematography. He amassed a large collection of vintage cameras, projectors, lenses, stereoscopic viewers, and motion picture equipment. Browning lectured on and exhibited his collection at colleges, schools, and professional organizations throughout the New York area.
In later years, Browning focused his career on creating motion pictures. He worked in a variety of capacities in the film industry, from his early work as an actor to his later work in the 1930s and 1940s as a director, producer, and cameraman. A few of his short films gained a measure of notice, including the documentary City of Contrasts (1931), and the short biopic Women in Photography (1941) which focused on the careers of Ruth Alexander Nichols, Toni Frissel, Bernice Abbott, and Margaret Bourke-White.
Browning was a member of a number of professional organizations, including the Society of Motion Picture Engineers, the American Television Society, and the Master Photo Dealers' & Finishers' Association. His photographs were exhibited jointly with such well-regarded contemporaries as Margaret Bourke-White, Ralph Steiner, and Bernice Abbott. By 1940, Browning had founded and was serving as president of the Camera Mart, Inc., a photographic and motion picture equipment store which he owned until his death in 1961.
Related Materials
Scrapbook 11-C in the Bella C. Landauer Collection of Business and Advertising Ephemera in the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections of The New-York Historical Society contains some of Irving Browning's identification and membership cards for professional organizations and conferences.
Scope and Contents
The Browning Photograph Collection spans the period from 1918 to 1952 and primarily contains photographs depicting exteriors and interiors of new buildings in and around New York City in the 1920s and 1930s. Photographers Irving and Sam Browning photographed theaters, hotels, skyscrapers, suburban residences, shoppers, peddlers, Great Depression shanty towns, weather and night views, and Manhattan street life. Also included is a disbound scrapbook created by Irving Browning containing career-related documents and ephemera. The collection is divided into two series: Photographs; and Documents.
Correspondence.; Ephemera.; Gelatin silver prints.; Identity cards.; Membership cards.; Night photography.; Photographic prints.; Photomontages.; Architecture -- New York (State) -- New York.; Buildings -- Design and construction.; Depressions -- 1929.; Signs and signboards.; Streets -- New York (State) -- New York.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Browning, Irving, 1895-1961; Browning, Sam; Mead, Margaret, 1901-1978; Chrysler Building (New York, N.Y.); Daily News Building (New York, N.Y.); Earl Carroll Theatre; Empire State Building (New York, N.Y.); Irving Browning Studio; RKO Roxy Theatre
- Series I. Photographs
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I consists of 1,885 gelatin silver photographs measuring 8 x 10 inches or smaller, depicting a wide range of New York buildings, institutions, parks and squares, theaters, signs, and street scenes. Photographs are arranged alphabetically into the following subject-based subseries: Advertising; Aircraft and Aeronautics; Apartment Buildings; Banks and Financial Institutions; Browning, Irving; Chinatown; Churchs and Synagogues; Construction and Construction Workers; Depression, the Great; Eagles; Factories and Industry; Harbor and Waterfront Views; Hospitals; Hotels; Lower East Side; Monuments and Statues; Night Views; Occupations; Office Buildings; Parks and Squares; Photomontages; Police Stations; Portraits; Public Buildings and Institutions; Rain Views; Residences; Restaurants; Roofs and Roof Gardens; Ships, Boats and Ferries; Shoes; Shops and Shopping; Skylines and Cityscapes; Sports and Recreation; Streets and Avenues; Television and Radio; Theaters; Tourists; Transportation; Utilities; Winter Views; and Miscellaneous/Unidentified. This series contains architectural photographs taken for clients, such as construction progress photographs of art-deco theaters and skyscrapers, as well as more documentary photographs that portray with a touching grace the lives of New Yorkers during the Great Depression. Browning's photographs depict the city in an era that began with a prosperous postwar economy, struggled through the Depression, and ended in the second World War; they document both the glamorous and the destitute environments that existed simultaneously in the city during this era.
  Most photographs have been briefly labeled and bear one or more of several Irving Browning studio stamps; some photographs also have "Browning" and a negative number printed into the photograph. It is unclear which of the photographs may have been taken by Sam Browning or other photographers in Browning's employ; all credits refer to "Irving Browning" or the "Studio of Irving Browning." The majority of the photographs bear no dates. Approximate dates for buildings in this finding aid were researched during processing and are generally related to dates of building construction as established by the American Institute of Architects in the AIA Guide to New York City, 4th edition (New York: Three Rivers Press, 2000). Photographs in this collection bear only very brief descriptions on the verso or no description at all; descriptions listed in this finding aid were generally assigned or expanded by N-YHS staff and are not titles assigned by the Browning Studio.
  Two boxes at the end of the collection contain duplicate vintage prints of photographs from Series I which are being held in reserve.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Digital copies are available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
  - Advertising
    Scope and Contents
    The Advertising subseries primarily focuses on billboards and other large signs, many of which were taken around the Times Square area. Several of these advertising photographs also appear in Browning's photomontages.
    - A&P Coffee billboard, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Anheuser Bsuch, Inc., Budweiser billboard and clock in Times Square (3), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Barbershop poles, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Chevrolet billboard, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Camel Cigarettes billboard, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Chevrolet billboards (2), 1934, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Horses [Kauffman Saddles and Boots and unidentified], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Criterion Theatre movie billboard for Viva Villa, [1934] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Cocoanut Grove billboard [with mechanic fixing car], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Schenley Mayflower Whiskey billboard and clock (2), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Squibb Dental Cream billboard, with part of Coca-Cola billboard, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Sunkist billboard, with Child's (restauraunt) billboard (2), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Wrigley's Spearmint Gum billboard, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aircraft and Aeronautics
    Aircraft and Aeronautics includes mostly unidentified photographs of early aviators, airplanes, airships (blimps), and members of high society posing with aircraft at small airfields in the greater New York area. Included are portraits of several society women posing near airplanes; several of these were taken were at private aviation clubs such as the Aviation Country Club in on Long Island. Identified individuals pictured in this series include Beckwith Havens, Howard Hughes, Joe McLaughlin, Evelyn Seversky, and Mrs. Felix William Zelcer.
    - Aviation Country Club flags (Hicksville, NY), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Curtis-Wright Airport views (North Beach, NY) (9), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Havens, Beckwith aboard a seaplane, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Hughes, Howard with Seversky Amphibian, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - McLaughlin, Joe posing in plane, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Seversky, Evelyn, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Whitney, Mrs. Paul Le Brogue, on Waco Cabin Plane, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Zelcer, Mrs. Felix William, at the Aviation Country Club, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified airship, airplane, seaplane, and airfield views (41), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Apartment Buildings
    Apartment Buildings primarily contains views of newly constructed apartment buildings in a variety of neighborhoods in Manhattan and nearby suburban areas. The largest group of photographs depicts the interior and exterior of buildings in the Tudor City Apartments complex.
    - Baker Field Apartments, 520 West 218th St., undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Brentanos Furnished Apartments, Broadway and 80th St., undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Century Apartments, 25 Central Park West (2), [after 1931] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cliffhaven Court, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Crystal Gardens, including aerial view (9), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - London Terrace, West 23rd St. and Ninth Ave. (2), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
      General note
      See also: Box 13, Folder 128
    - 277 Park Avenue Apartments, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Pickwick Arms (Inwood) (7), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Scarswold Apartments (Scarsdale, NY), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Tudor City Apartments, interiors and exteriors (15), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Unidentified, interiors and exteriors (13), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Banks and Financial Institutions
    Banks and Financial Institutions holds basic architectural views of Manhattan bank exteriors, including several prominent bronze clocks.
    - American Savings Bank, 115 West 42nd St., bronze clock, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
    - Bank of Manhattan Trust Company, 295 Madison Ave., clocks (2), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
    - Central Savings Bank, Union Square, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
    - Continental Bank & Trust Company, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
    - Guaranty Trust Company of New York, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
    - Irving Trust Company, 1 Wall St. West 33rd St. (3), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
    - Mutual Bank, West 33rd St., undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
    - New York Trust Company, 1 East 57th St. (3), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
    - Trade Bank of New York, clock, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
  - Browning, Irving
    The Irving Browning subseries includes views of Irving Browning's office interior as well as promotional posters for his photographic services, one of which features a portrait of Irving Browning.
    - Office interiors and promotional posters (13), [1930], undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
  - Chinatown
    Chinatown views show the streets of the Chinatown area in Lower Manhattan, including businesses and institutions such as the Rescue Society, the Old Chinese Theatre and the Nan Yang Association.
    - The Bowery, nos. 20-22 at Pell St. (2), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
    - 5-7 Doyers St., Rescue Society and Old Chinese Theatre (2), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
    - Doyers St. at Chatham Square, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
    - Pell St., no. 36 at Mott St., undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
    - Nan Yang Association, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
  - Churches and Synagogues
    Churches and Synagogues contains views of a variety of well-known Manhattan religious structures. Popular churches depicted including Riverside Church, the Cathedral of St. John the Divine, and the Church of the Transfiguration ("the Little Church Around the Corner") in Manhattan, as well as a large series of photographs of St. John's Lutheran Church in Englewood, New Jersey. Also included are a few synagogues: Ezrath Israel Synagogue and Inwood Hebrew Congregation, which was located not far from Irving Browning's longtime home in Upper Manhattan.
    - Cathedral of St. John the Divine, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    - Church of the Good Shepard (?), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    - Church of the Transfiguration [Little Church Around the Corner], undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    - Community Church of the Pelhams (Pelham, NY), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    - Ezrath Israel Synagogue, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    - First Church of Christ Scientist (Maplewood, NJ), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    - Inwood Hebrew Congregation, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    - Riverside Church (6), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
    - St. Bartholomew (3), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
    - St. John's Lutheran Church, interior and exterior (Englewood, NJ), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
    - St. Luke's Church (Forest Hills) (27), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
    - St. Patrick's Cathedral (7), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
    - St. Paul's Chapel, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
    - Temple Emmanuel, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
    - Trinity Church and churchyard, some with Wall St., undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
    - Unidentified, interiors and exteriors (14), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
  - Construction and Construction Workers
    Construction and Construction Workers includes views of workmen and construction sites. Most are entirely unidentified, but tend to focus on small details of construction or very specifically on the workers.
    - Construction and construction workers (40), [1920-1935] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
  - Depression, the Great
    Depression, the Great, includes a variety of photographs focusing on the troubling economic and social consequences of the Great Depression. Photographs depict the homeless, desperate men and women lined up to look at job boards or to enter employment agencies, shantytowns or "Hoovervilles" constructed by the homeless, and a jobless man in a business suit selling apples in the street.
    - Great Depression views (14), [1929-1939] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 21)
      See also: Occupations
  - Eagles
    Eagles consists of a few photographs of unidentified eagle sculptures, artworks and illustrations.
    - Eagles [sculptures and illustrations] (4), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 22)
  - Factories and Industry
    Factories and Industry consists of photographs of unidentified factory workers, machinery, and equipment. Most photographs are not specifically identified. A number of views of factory smokestacks are included in this subseries.
    - Workers and equipment (44), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 23-24)
    - Smokestacks (20), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 25)
  - Harbor and Waterfront Views
    Harbor and Waterfront Views depict the waters around Manhattan, often with the buildings of various shorelines or bridges on the horizon.
    - Harbor and waterfront views (30), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 26)
  - Hospitals
    Hospitals consists of a few views of Bellevue and Lenox Hill hospitals and a larger series of views of New York Hospital-Cornell Medical Center.
    - Bellevue Hospital, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 27)
    - Lenox Hill Hospital, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 27)
    - New York Hospital-Cornell Medical Center (11), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 27)
  - Hotels
    Hotels includes views of many classic historic New York sites including the Hotel Pennsylvania, and the Plaza, Ritz-Carlton, and Waldorf-Astoria Hotels, among others. Some views of grand interiors are available in this subseries. Views of Cooks Falls Lodge in Roscoe, New York, and the Grand View Lodge in Greenwich, Connecticut are also included.
    - Arrowhead Inn, interiors and exteriors (Riverdale) (7), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 28)
    - Hotel Astor, Broadway at 44th St., interiors and exteriors (4), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 29)
    - Barbazon Hotel, 140 East 63rd St., undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 30)
    - Hotel Claridge, Broadway and 44th St., undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 30)
    - Cooks Falls Lodge (Roscoe, NY), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 30)
    - Grand View Lodge, interiors and exteriors (Greenwich, CT) (9), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 30)
    - Hotel Martinique, 53 West 33nd St., undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 31)
    - Hotel McAlpin, 50 West 34th St., undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 31)
    - Murray Hill Hotel, Park Ave. and 40th St., undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 31)
    - Hotel Navarre, Seventh Ave. and W. 38th St. (2), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 31)
    - Hotel Netherland, Fifth Ave. and 59th St., 1924 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 31)
    - Park Chambers Hotel, 68 West 58th St., undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 31)
    - Hotel Pennsylvania, 401 Seventh Ave., undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 31)
    - Plaza Hotel, 768 Fifth Ave. (3), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 31)
    - Ritz-Carlton Hotel, East 46th St. (2), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 32)
    - St. Moritz Hotel, 50 Central Park South, interiors, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 32)
    - Savoy Plaza Hotel, with Sherry-Netherland Hotel, Fifth Ave. at 59th St. (6), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 32)
    - Shelton Towers Hotel, 525 Lexington Ave. (2), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 32)
    - Hotel Sulgrave, 60 East 67th St., interiors and exteriors (16), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 33)
    - Waldorf-Astoria Hotel, 301 Park Ave., interiors and exteriors (16), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 34)
    - Unidentified, interiors (6), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 35)
  - Lower East Side
    Lower East Side photographs consist of quintessential neighborhood views frin this period. Included are crowds in the street markets, street views with a variety of clothing stores, children in the street, and tenement buildings with clothes hung on lines to dry.
    - The Bowery, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 36)
    - Chrystie St., undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 36)
    - Clinton St., nos. 40-42 (2), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 36)
    - Orchard St., from Rivington St., undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 36)
    - Suffolk St., with street stock exchange, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 36)
    - Miscellaneous, including tenement exteriors and clotheslines (10), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 36)
  - Monuments and Statues
    Monuments and Statues consists of photographs of the Civic Virtue, seen from the entrance to City Hall, (it was relocated to Queens Borough Hall in 1941 and to Green-Wood Cemetery in Brooklyn in 2012); the Washington Irving monument in Bryant Park which was relocated to East 17th Street in 1935, and the Statue of Liberty, as well as a few unidentified statues.
    See also: Parks and Squares for views including monuments.
    - Civic Virtue monument, view from entrance to City Hall, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 37)
      [relocated to Queens Borough Hall in 1941, and to Green-Wood Cemetery in Brooklyn in 2012]
    - Washington Irving, Bryant Park, [1920-1935] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 37)
      [relocated to East 17th Street in 1935]
    - Statue of Liberty, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 37)
    - Unidentified (2), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 37)
  - Night Views
    Night Views consists of a variety of photographs taken at night around the city, showing off such sites as the New York Public Library, the Empire State Building, the lighted signs of Times Square and elsewhere, and a variety of street and skyline views that capture the lights of urban nighttime.
    - Advertising, lighted signs [including Times Square area] (10), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 38)
    - Christmas trees, lighted (3), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 39)
    - Empire State building (6), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 40)
    - New York Public Library (2), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 41)
    - Skyline views (21), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 42)
    - Street scenes (4), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 43)
  - Occupations